so hi everyone thank you very
much um for joining us today for
uh this week's magnet seminar um we've got another
great turnout um 46 people at the moment and that
will probably grow over the next few minutes um
for those who are sort of unfamiliar with the
seminars and we'll have a 20 to 25 to 30 minute
presentation so we kindly ask that you keep your
microphones uh muted during this time but after
the the presentation there'll be a chance for
a 10 to 15 minute uh question and discussion
session um so please i just raise your hand with
the zoom feature there or if you're not quite
sure you can always just unmute and shout out
um but if you do want to ask a question
but you don't want to appear on camera or
um unmute yourself um please just type in your
question in the text chat and uh one of us will
read it out for you um as always we've got life
going on around us many of us are at home so
you do need to get up and go um please just
just go it's not an issue at all um and at
the end of the seminar we'll have a chance for
a bit of a catch up uh a bit of a chit chat and
socializing uh which won't actually be recorded
so it's a bit more of a relaxed um free-for-all
so today i'm very pleased to say that
we have uh andrea byderman um from the
university of bern and she will be talking
to us today about uh magnetic eye extra prey
characterization so i shall hand over to you
okay thanks a lot i'm very
excited to to talk about this very exotic topic
to you today so i'm just sharing my screen
all right so what i want to talk about is
how we might apply magnetic anise entropy to
characterizing pore space and the idea behind
this is that while we all know that we can
characterize mineral alignment in rocks
using magnetic and isotropy and there are
many empirical relationships telling us that the
magnetic anisotropy indicates fabric orientation
and also that magnetic anisotropy can then tell
us something about the degree of the anisotropy
a big advantage of the method is that it only
takes us a couple of minutes to do a measurement
and with these couple of minutes we are getting
an average second order tensor and that allows
us to then describe the fabric in 3d and it does
not matter in which direction we are drilling our
core or how we are orienting a sample because we
are going to get that full 3d description anyway
now let's quickly think about whether or how we
could apply this to characterizing poor fabrics
so poor fabrics they are really important
in any study where we are looking at
fluid migration or when we want to characterize
reservoirs because any anisotropy in the core
space might actually affect the fluid flow that
we have in the subsurface so when we do have
an iso an anisotropic pore space then we would
expect that there is a preferred flow direction
in which flow is faster and if we are for example
looking at contamination also contamination would
spread faster along that direction of preferred
flow and because of that we would like to be able
to describe the pore space and the pore fabric
and with many of the traditional methods we are
going to run into problems because we can either
look at very small samples at very high resolution
or we could look at larger samples at quite low
resolution and of course what we would like is to
look at a large sample that is representative at
high resolution and with many methods that is not
possible to do both at once and then also if we
are looking methods that are for example based on
x-ray tomography they are very time-consuming
and they require a lot of storage space
also we would want a full 3d description of
our core fabric and we would like to get that
independent of the orientation of our sample
now why is that important it is important because
if we are for example measuring permeability so
we are measuring fluid flow directly on a sample
we can normally only measure that along the long
axis of the core so depending on how we drilled
that core we would then get a different value and
often people would then drill free perpendicular
cores but of course if those do not contain
the principal directions we would then
underestimate the anisotropy and then also
a last point we have to think about when we are
interested in poor fabrics is that some of the
pores are connected so they do contribute
to fluid flow and other pores are isolated
and they do not contribute to fluid flow so we
would rather only describe the connected force
and one method with which we might be able
to do that is the method of magnetic poor
fabrics what has been found in the past is quite
promising empirical relationships between magnetic
data and pore space or also fluid flow properties
so namely what people have found is that
the maximum susceptibility that we measure is
parallel to the elongation direction of the pores
and also parallel to the flow direction
so the preferred flow direction
meaning that if we measure magnetic part fabrics
we could then predict preferred flow directions
and a second set of empirical relationships
that has been found is that a larger degree
of an isotropy so a larger ratio of
maximum to minimum susceptibility
would indicate more an isentropic pore space
and also a higher permeability anisotropy
and then it has been stated that with this
method we can isolate the connected force so
we are only looking at the fraction of the
pore space that is controlling fluid flow
it takes only a couple of minutes to measure
the anisotropy it is the same average second
order tensor that we would measure with standard
ams measurements so we are getting our full 3d
information again without needing any a priori
information on how we have to orient our samples
and we can look at a representative sample volume
and supposedly include pores down to 10 nanometers
and being able to do that looking at small
pores in a representative volume would kind of
add this extra information in addition
to what one could get with tomography
there is just one problem with the method
and that's this really large variability
that we have seen in the studies that were
published so far and when we're looking at this
we would see that a p-value so an isotropy degree
of for example 1.6 could represent pores with
an actual ratio of anything between 2 and 12 and
because of that these empirical relationships that
we have at the moment are not very useful when
we are trying to use the magnetic core fabrics
in order to make a statement about the workforce
based so the aim of my work and my group's work
is that we would really like to be able to
explain this large variability because if
we can explain it then it would would be possible
to interpret magnetic part fabrics quantitatively
now let's just take a step back and look
again at the anisotropy description of mineral
fabrics there we had a very similar problem
in the early days of magnetic fabric research
because yes there are empirical relationships
between magnetic and isotropic strain or magnetic
anisotropy and mineral alignment but it was found
that these relationships they vary by rock type
meaning that many different
empirical relationships were found
depending on the lythology or also depending on
on the on the exact methodology that that was used
and that's kind of what we see here right again
with this really large variation also it was found
that our maximum and minimum susceptibility
they are not necessarily parallel to delineation
or parallel to the pole to foliation and at that
point people could have given up and said well
we are not using magnetic anisotropy anymore
to describe mineral alignment but that's not
what happened rather what happened is new methods
were developed to look at either um all the grains
in our rock which is what we're doing with the
low field methods or to isolate specific grains
from our rock and then only uh described the
fabric of those and at the same time people have
started developing models on the physical origins
of the anisotropy and how we can predict uh the
dimension the measurements that that we expect so
a big question now is is it possible to transfer
that to the study of magnetic four fabrics and if
yes would it help us with that large variability
that was observed and before i want to go
into that a quick overview of how we are
measuring magnetic wire fabrics so first of all
we have a sample it could be a synthetic sample
i'm only going to show you results in some
that examples today but it could also be
a rock sample ideally a rock sample where
we know something about the force base for
example with a x-ray tomography data then we
are impregnating that sample with ferrofluid
we can use different types of fluids also
different concentrations and then measure the
anisotropy of magnetic susceptibility which
supposedly gives us an average poor fabric
now what we have done is we've done
these measurements at various frequencies
and we will see towards the end of this talk
why it is important that we are measuring at
various frequencies so i said that i'm only going
to show you today results on synthetic samples and
why are we looking at bone synthetic samples
well a very big advantage is that we are having
pores that are large enough so that
we can characterize them independently
we can control the shape of
the pores because we make them
we can also control the assembly of the
pores and we can compare any data with
previously published results that exist on
synthetic samples and i'm going to show you
two case studies here first of all i want to look
into that sample that we see here on the left
and it is from a study that was taken by uh that
was done by jones at all in 2006 and they had very
carefully defined different types of fabrics
that they were then describing with simplified
synthetic samples with a small number of cores for
for these pores we know that the size and shape
of the individual pore what we do not know from
that study is the distance between the cores
but now let's just take this this sample
that is supposed to show us a bedding type
fabric in this sample we have a couple of cores
aligned next to each other they all have the
same problematic shape and let's see what we
can do with what we know from the standard
interpretation for magnetic fabrics and what's
been published on magnetic port fabrics previously
to see if we can predict the measurements
that were reported in that study
so for magnetic core fabrics the theory so far has
been that the magnetic measurement would reflect
an average poor shape and
an average poor orientation
and the idea was that this would happen
very similar to say having a magnetite grain
surrounded by other grains while we can also
have a ferrofluid filled pore surrounded by
other grains both of those are expected
to have some shape on this entropy with
the maximum susceptibility then parallel to the
long axis of the grain or the long axis of the
pore and this is where this empirical relationship
is coming from that the maximum susceptibility of
the magnetic core fabric supposedly indicates
the average poor elongation direction
so i was calculating the anisotropy for the
average pore shape and average point orientation
because all the pores are the same that is
equivalent to just modeling a single pore
what i'm getting was this here what jones
at all measured is what we see there
and we see that there is quite a large difference
between my very simple model and the measurement
so obviously i have to adapt the model in order
to do that better and i then thought okay well
we don't have just one pore we have several
pores so let's include distribution and isotropy
because the pores that are next to each other
they are going to interact with one another and
distribution anisotropy has in the past
been modeled for infinite assemblies of
equal grains and that's basically what i was
doing here and the result i'm getting is depending
on the distance between the pores so i'm kind
of starting over here when i put my pores as
far apart as i can within the dimensions of
the sample and then i'm moving over that way
when i'm putting my pores closer and closer
together of course the limit would be the
moment where they are touching one another and
what we see is compared to the previous model
this is already doing better but we still
have a deviation and in order to solve that
we said well wouldn't it be possible to just model
the actual number of cores that we have in that
sample rather than having to create an infinite
line of course and that's what we did and we
we're then developing a model that is a bit
closer to reality so what we see here on the left
is the models that people were that were doing
before basically modeling shape and distribution
anisotropy four assemblies of particles so
that could be grains that could be pores
that all have the same shape they all have
the same orientation and they are arranged
either in lines as we see here or they are
arranged in planes where we have equal spacing
in all directions between neighboring
course and we said well in a real rock
it's unlikely that we have that so we are
trying to make a model that is able to calculate
that distribution anisotropy for unequal
sizes unequal orientations and unequal shapes
and the results of that model were
actually quite promising because
this is what i'm showing you here so now that the
blue dots with the dashed line in between we are
getting very close to the actual measurement with
a specific spacing between um between the cores so
it was really nice to see that result because
that tells me that with the current theory when
we are including both shape and isotropy
and distribution anisotropy we can explain
that measurement now it was not so easy
when i tried to explain my own data
so now going over to the other set of synthetic
samples that that we had and again we followed the
same procedure so we had our samples we've known
dimensions known geometry um we we're filling them
with ferrofluid using different types and also
different concentrations and then using that
model to predict what what we should get
so what we see up here for the top group
of samples actually these samples they are very
simple we have the same actual ratio for the core
it is a single core so it's easy to model and the
only thing that changes is the size of it and what
we did here is we were using the different fluids
at different concentrations and we found that
the higher the susceptibility of the fluid which
depends on the type and the concentration and the
larger is the degree of an isotropy that we would
expect for that given shape of the core then as
we are diluting our ferrofluid we are decreasing
the degree of anisotropy that we are expecting
and in the lower set of samples which we have
here we were then looking at assemblies of course
where we were first filling a single one then
we were filling um two at the corners a third
in the middle we were adding a second line and
in the end we had all of the course filled again
calculating models for different sizes and
different aspect ratios and we are getting
slightly different values depending on the
core assembly that uh that we are looking at
for that second series we were only using the
fluid with the highest susceptibility because
we thought when we have the the highest
degree of nslgb anyway then it's easiest
to actually see how it behaves and here are
now some of the data for the first set there
we were we are looking at the degree of
an isotropy um for the different fluids
so we have the water-based fluid
which has a higher susceptibility
on the left and then we have the oil-based
fluid with a lower susceptibility on the right
and what we see here are well two characteristics
one is that the smaller samples that we're showing
here with smaller symbols they had a lot of
artifacts those artifacts could be the ferrofluid
uh interacting with the seal and over time we
had air bubbles develop we also had fluid move
from under the seal and out of it and we also
had particle aggregation over time and then of
course when your particles aggregate as we see
over here then we are no longer measuring the
shape of the entire pore but we are just measuring
the shape of that cake of particles at the bottom
so that part we can explain what we can't
explain is this difference between the model
and the measurements our measurements are
constantly showing us lower and isotropy
um for the water-based fluid than what we expected
for the oil-based fluid we are doing pretty okay
and very similar results we had for
that second set of samples where we
were looking at assemblies of course i'm
only showing the two linear arrangements
but it was very similar for the for the other
sample sets two so again what we see here
is that for the smallest samples we
are having artifacts and then the
other thing we see is i'm showing you here the
measured anisotropy as a function of frequency
what we see is that the measured analyze entropy
decreases with increasing measurement frequency
and it's also always lower than what we modeled
so the pluses on the y-axis those are the models
and then the the circles are indicating
the measurements on the different samples
another big question was how do we
explain that right and what we found is
that especially that water-based fluid
that we have here on the left which shows
a very very strong frequency dependence
we also found that the frequency dependence
is different for each of the ferrofluids and
well for the water-based ferrofluids almost
always the susceptibility that we're measuring
is way lower than the susceptibility that is
specified in the fluids technical specifications
um we could have a susceptibility and measure
susceptibility of around 20 to 30 percent
of the specifications of the fluid whereas
for the oil-based fluids um we were often
getting susceptibilities between 120-130 percent
of what was specified but we know that the
expected anaxotropy depends on the susceptibility
of the fluid so what are we doing with these two
pieces of information our fluid at measurement
conditions has a different susceptibility from
the one we expect and the anisotropy that we
expect depends on the fluid susceptibility
so going back to our published relationships
not all of them were actually specifying the
fluids they used or the susceptibility
of the fluid but some of them were and
i was running a model basically predicting
what i would expect for these studies
with the specified susceptibilities and we see
here the measurements in red and what i predicted
was not very similar but when i then corrected for
the assumed measurement frequency based on my own
data i was then getting a relationship between
the magnetic anisotropy and the actual ratio of
the poor that was fitting a lot better with the
measured data so the integration of that is that
the variability in the empirical relationships
that has been observed is simply because
the data is not comparable people were using
different fluids with different susceptibilities
and because of that we would actually expect
them to get different empirical relationships
we have also found that we cannot use the
susceptibility that is specified by the
fluid supplier for modeling and we would really
encourage anyone who is doing magnetic pore fabric
work to check your effective fluid susceptibility
and specify that in your publications
the reason we are asking to do that is that once
we know the properties of the fluid at measurement
conditions then we are pretty confident that
a quantitative interpretation is possible
and we can then apply the magnetic
core fabric method to the rocks so
to sum up the method of magnetic port fabrics
has the potential to efficiently characterize
rocks for space so far the interpretation
was somewhat compromised because we were only
having empirical relationships and the differences
between different studies were quite large but we
now have a model that explains this variability
and that tells us that the quantitative
interpretation is now possible and we are
hoping that the method will be much more applied
for fluid flow studies aquifer and reservoir
characterization medium so geothermal and co2
applications and i'm also taking
the opportunity to just advertise
other work that's going on in my group and that's
going to be presented at each u one of my students
is spending a lot of time correlating magnetic
core fabric results with other methods and then my
other student is working on improving incarnation
methods so if you're interested in those you are
finding the details of the presentations here
and with that i'm very happy to take questions
thank you very much andrea so we can all
give andrea a virtual round of applause
uh via zoom for for a really
interesting talk thank you
thank you so um i'll open up the
the floor uh to questions so you
can raise your hand either via zoom
or throw a question into into the chat
if no one is going to open with a question
i certainly have a couple i can throw up
but i'll there we go we'll jump
in with with uh will mccarthy
hey yeah thanks for giving a talk it's really
really interesting stuff um i was just curious
at the mo at presents in order to do this
you basically need to impregnate the sample
with feral fluid is there a way that you
can do it or consider doing it without a
feral fluid at all is there a way that we can
look at the pore space without the ferrofluid
yeah um well in order to be able to look at
shape and isotropy or to to look at distribution
we will have to have something magnetic inside
the course right there are non-magnetic methods
um x-ray tomography is kind of the the standard
method that people use however they are having
big trouble with resolution so if you're taking a
standard sized core they are reaching resolution
of 1 to 10 micrometers and often that is kind
of losing most of the of the smaller pores
yeah the reason i ask i mean i kind of knew
the answer i suppose but i was just hoping
you had some magical solution um obviously
if you're interested in looking at something
on the scale of a reservoir be it you
know carbon capture or be as you know
hydro system or whatever um you're dealing
with quite a large area so so obviously the
character is that it would be great to be able to
analyze you know many samples very rapidly which
ams is good at um so yeah i was just curious
to see if if there was a way of leapfrogging
or potentially in the future will be plugged
in their feral fluid bit that's fine thanks
i mean one one idea that that we are may have is
um to use other magnetic molecules such as single
molecule magnets because they might be smaller
than the particles and the ferrofluid and they
may be high behave a bit better than the
ferrofluid all the frequency dependence issues
but other than that i i don't have the magical
solution because otherwise i would have presented
that absolutely yeah sure thanks thanks very much
will uh so gunther is throwing a question into the
the chat asking about interactions between uh the
particles in the ferrofluid and if there are any
how that might actually influence
your susceptibility measurements
yeah that's a very good question um it's something
that we've been trying to look into and we didn't
really get anywhere um normally what people do
in magnetic core fabric studies is that they are
treating the ferrofluid as a homogeneous fluid
so they are kind of ignoring the fact that we
have particles and non-magnetic carrier fluid now
what we realized is that over time and that means
as our ferrofluid ages and that could be times of
days or weeks the particles start aggregating and
that also changes their magnetic properties
um those are data that we have collected and
we have not really made a consistent story of
those yet that's why i'm not showing any of them
but certainly there are interactions between
the magnetic particles inside the fluid
and they are changing the magnetic properties
over time and we will see where that's taking us
thank you very much um so we have
another another question in the chat from
uh leonid and who is asking about the uh matrix
material in the synthetic samples if you'd
um maybe describe a little bit of
what the actual matrix material is
right um i guess that that question is
what's getting me really into trouble
with the geochemists because the the reason
i'm using synthetic samples is i'm trying to
or the only part i'm interested in
is getting a core of a known shape
we were using a polycarbonate plastic for
that and i'm totally aware that some people
are going to tell me that it has a different
wetability compared to your standard rock
so the the material we were using was was plastic
because it's making it simple for us we can see
what's going on so for example um when we had
particle aggregation we could see that right away
it's not your best equivalent for a
rock from the chemical perspective
thank you very much and so uh andre
has his hand up for a question
okay andre great talk thank
you and i have a little bit of
concern with the choice of the choice
of materials for modeling because
the organics in particular and water are
diamagnetic and if you apply different frequency
different frequencies then your susceptibility
diamagnetic susceptibility rises as a function of
free linearly as a function of frequency you can
easily find it out when you try to measure your
sample holder with mf mfk to uh at two
frequencies and how how do you account for this
so if i got that right you're asking for
the changes in susceptibility of the of
the plastic part of the sample of the pla yes
yes um i was measuring that separately and i
was subtracting it from my instrument yeah
and uh how how big was that was this effect
actually how big was sorry how how big was
the effect of uh changing the frequency on the
on the empty sample on the empty sample um it was
a lot weaker than what i see for the feral fluid
if you're interested in the actual numbers
i can send them to you okay okay thank you
thanks very much and so um vladimir has his
hand up and we've got another question in
the chat as well so we'll start with
vladimir okay uh thanks hopefully i'm
audible um i have a question uh great talk andra
it's very interesting what we are trying to do
um i have a question when when you were
trying to model the the anisotropy the
distribution of isotope actually with uh
you knew um two the fin errors or how it's
pronounced you you actually mentioned that
uh your results shuffle within within the
within the space of the results what was the
variable you were changing in the model as you
were trying to represent the actual distribution
of the porous pores in your sample so what was the
variable you were changing to move the
move the result in in the space thanks
right so so what you're asking about is is kind
of this graph right what's changing um on the line
exactly in the model you were uh using with the
so um i mean what did we do to get this
we no we know the susceptibility the average
susceptibility of the fluid inside the course
we know the the size or the dimension of the
course the only part we do not know is the
spacing between them right because
in in that paper they had given the
the size of their entire sample and they
had given the size of the pore but not the
spacing so we have some constraints because
the way this we can put the course apart
is having the outer pores touch the sample surface
and the closest we can have them together is have
them touch each other and basically when we
are moving between these points from here
and over to there the only part that i'm changing
is the spacing between the pores um here i'm doing
that for the finite number of four or five ports
that i have in the sample while on this line there
i was doing the exact same thing um but using
an infinite line of course right because i was
first using the the model that was available yeah
thank you very much i didn't catch that it was you
didn't know the the spacing of the pores that
it was the information missing so now it makes
great sense that you are able to find the
good result thanks thanks thank you very much
okay thanks for giving me the
opportunity to clarify that
thanks very much we have one time for one last
quick question from the chat from gunther uh
who was asking uh he saw the ajucos kappa bridge
he was asking if you used any other instruments
that would use running frequencies that are
not part of the electrical measurement routine
yes i did so what i was using here is kind of
the the red data that you see here is the actual
copper bridge results um measured at 1 4 and
16 kilohertz and then i was also using the sm
150 instrument that is um it's made by said age
instruments so it's another czech company they are
nominally reaching frequencies
between 60 hertz and 512 kilohertz um
i only did some initial measurements with that
instrument because what you see down here on
the second plot that's normalized by the by the
ferrofluid volume is that for all sample except
the largest one i have such a big nice level that
it's very hard to see any frequency dependence
thank you thank you very much um
so i think we'll we'll draw the uh
question uh session uh to a close for uh for today
uh so i just want to ask everybody to give andrea
another uh round of applause for uh a really uh
great and well presented talk thank you very much
well thank you it was a pleasure to
present that topic to you and i really appreciated
all the questions and the ideas we've had another
another uh great turnout uh today so thanks
everybody for that um but before we sort of
ends the um session for today it's got a couple of
um quick reminders and and announcements to make
um so this will be uh the last magnet seminar
before we go for a break for uh egu um and we
will return on uh may 19th with a speaker to
be confirmed um but we'll just have a single
uh seminar in the period between egu and the
irm conference which is in the uh beginning of
uh june um but following the irm conference we
will open up our european and eastern hemisphere
time slot with andrew roberts from australia
national university the exact time slot is to
be decided it's most likely going to be 8 a.m or 9
a.m uh in british time and we're just working with
our speakers in the eastern hemisphere to work out
what's going to be the best time for those guys
um but as always we're looking for more speakers
so if you are interested in presenting your
latest research at magnets please i reach out to
myself or to anita and just as a another reminder
um all of our uh videos and seminars are recorded
and will be are available on on youtube and
uh this talk will be put up a little bit later
this week um and so if you've missed anything
or if there's something you want to go back and
look at um there's all the seminars are there
for you to to use and we have citable uh dois as
well so if you do find something interesting that
you want to use uh you can uh cite your work
and just as a a very quick uh announcement um
um for our colleagues in uh the institute
of rock magnetism uh later on this year
they'll have their 12th irm conference on rock
magnetism it's running from june 1st to the 4th
2021 and this year it's going to be held
like all conferences uh virtually and so
there is the option for doing a free registration
there's no uh registration fees but there are a
limited number of of positions available and
if you want to find out some more information
uh have a look at their um the irm website or
reach out to max brown at the irm at umn.edu
so thank you all very much and thank
you for joining this week's magnets